- Previously on Gotham...
- It's you. It's really you.
Oh, no. Somebody help!
Penguin.
He killed the librarian.
I don't want to kill him.
I want to destroy him.
And you promised them Jerome.
They want to see his face.
Behold the Prophet!
We are Jerome!
You get the message?
We don't work for you no more.
I will gut you!
- Then Nygma dies.
- They have Ed.
When I was last, you know, alive,
I was about to kill Bruce Wayne.
Well, where is my face?
What?
Oswald.
- Where are you?
- Kane Chemicals.
Oswald, hurry. Please?
Tonight, Gotham, there are no rules.
And when morning comes,
you, too, shall be...
reborn.
He's at the power
plant across the river.
Get those freaks in the cages!
We need to find Jerome.
Hey, watch him!
Let go of me!
Grab him!
What about you, huh?
Do you know where
Jerome is? Where is he?!
Where is he? Look around!
He's everywhere!
Incoming!
Get down!
Here.
Tonight... Gotham...
is awakened!
- Sync and corrections by madhatters -
- www.addic7ed.com -
Remember, Ed's safety
is all that matters.
Whoever took him will pay,
but only once Ed is back.
Ed!
Edward!
Ed.
Are you all right?
Tell me you are all right.
I'm fine, Oswald.
Of course you are.
Where are they? Who dared
to think they could lay
- their hands on you!
- I'm alone.
Oh, you escaped.
You did. Didn't you, you rascal?
Did you bring anyone else?
What? Why? No, uh...
Just wondering if I was
gonna have to reload.
I don't understand.
I know.
That's been half the fun.
I-I'm sorry. I... I...
What is happening? I...
You weren't kidnapped?
Not unless you count
kidnapping yourself.
Recognize it?
Oh, why should you?
I doubt you did the deed yourself.
That car belonged to Isabella.
Ed, whatever you've heard...
I know it was you, Oswald.
Isabella was my everything,
and you took her from me.
And now I've taken everything from you.
Well, almost everything.
You still have your life.
But that ends tonight.
Attention, all residents,
stay off the streets.
A curfew is in effect in Gotham City
until further notice.
Seems like judgment came to
Gotham earlier than expected.
If the situation worsens,
we may be forced to step in.
The city will bend
long before it breaks.
Give the GCPD a chance.
Your faith in him is touching.
And possibly dangerous.
We're getting reports of a
riot growing on the west side,
as well as widespread looting uptown.
Mobs of cult members have
taken over Anders Parks,
Gotham Cathedral, the zoo.
All right, concentrate
units on the west side.
Make sure they're issued riot gear.
- Any word on Jerome Valeska?
- Nothing yet.
Let me know as soon as he's spotted.
Right. Got it.
Lights aren't coming
back tonight. Tomorrow,
- if we're lucky.
- This thing just keeps getting bigger.
It's not just the cult anymore.
Ordinary citizens are taking
- Jerome's cue.
- Meanwhile, Cobblepot's MIA.
You call down to city hall, and
literally no one's in charge.
Although that might
actually be good news.
We need to find Jerome. He's the symbol.
If we can take him out,
maybe we can limit this
to a single bad night.
How the hell are we supposed
to find him out there?!
The city's one giant Dumpster fire.
Jerome said he wanted to
plunge the city into darkness
so people could do
what they want, right?
He's not one to miss out on
the fun, so what does he want?
A puppy? How the hell should
I know? I didn't talk to him.
No, but Lee did.
Yes!
But my father appeared to me.
I saw him.
No. You...
saw a man that I met in Indian Hill
that does killer impersonations.
You see, Oswald...
How do I put this?
Ghosts aren't real!
But my father's remains...
You stole them from his grave?
Yup.
Don't worry. He's at peace now.
I gently placed his remains
inside a Dumpster behind
a Chinese restaurant.
You were angry. I understand.
I even forgive you, but-but
killing me is not the way.
So you admit you killed Isabella?
Fine. Is that what you want?
- Yes!
- I confess.
I had her killed.
But guess what?
You should thank me because we both know
what would have happened if I hadn't.
Yes!
I could have lived a life
with the woman I loved.
I could have been happy.
No, Ed.
You would have killed her.
Just like you did the other one!
You couldn't have helped it!
And afterward, you would
have hated yourself!
Well...
we'll never know, will we?
I did it for love.
What?
I did it because I love you.
- You should know that.
- Shut up!
Love is about sacrifice.
It's about putting someone else's needs
and happiness before your own.
- Ed, please...
- 'Cause the truth is, Oswald,
you would sacrifice anyone
to save your own neck.
Even me.
Now, if you'll look above us,
you will see a cauldron
of highly corrosive acid,
which is currently being
held in place by this chain.
When the ice melts,
the chain comes loose,
the vat of acid tips.
You get the idea.
Ed.
Please. No, please.
I can change.
Say you're right. Say you're right. I...
The fact that I love you proves that
I can change. Just give me a chance.
You know as well as I
that a man facing death
will say anything to save his skin.
And you won't change...
because you can't.
Now, I was going to have
you say hello to Isabella.
But...
I think you... are going...
to a very different place.
Good-bye, Oswald.
Ed!
Ed! Ed!
Okay, I think that's about all I can do.
Thanks.
How's triage going?
We have a lot of overflow
from Gotham General.
What do you want?
When Jerome woke up,
did he say anything?
Just that he wanted his face back.
No. I mean, anything that might indicate
where he was going,
what he was planning.
We were just playing catch-up.
You know, about coming
back to life, the cult.
He asked if you and I
were still together.
I mentioned you killed my
husband on our wedding night,
and he thought that was
hilarious, so that's something
the two of you can bond
over when you find him.
He didn't tell me his plan.
He talked about Galavan,
the night he died,
and then he mentioned...
- What?
- Bruce.
He said the last thing he remembers
is that he was gonna kill Bruce Wayne.
Call Alfred, tell him I'm on my way.
I'll light these candles. Good lad.
I'll nip downstairs and see
if there's any life left
in that old generator.
Who's calling at this hour?
Alfred?
Shh.
Ooh!
My, my. Hmm.
Look how big you've gotten.
Are you okay?
I'll be fine, Master Bruce.
I'll be fine.
Nice place you got here.
You rent?
What do you want?
Attitude.
Teenagers. Am I right?
Oh, I remember those days.
So many exciting new emotions
floating through you.
Wanting to kill everyone you saw. Aw.
You. Give me.
You know, I will never
understand rich people's tastes.
It's worthless.
My father found it at a flea market.
I keep it for sentimental reasons.
Nice try. Oh, it's got some heft to it.
Expensive, I'm guessing.
- Be such a shame if I...
- Oh! No, don't.
Huh.
Tougher than I figured.
Anyway...
Aah! Bloody hell! I
asked you what you want.
Right. Sorry.
The old noodle's still a
little al dente post-thaw.
The reason I'm here
is I'm gonna kill you.
Why?
Well, it's the last thing
I remember wanting to do.
It's been nagging at me since I woke up.
The idea of slitting that pretty, pink
throat of yours.
Figure that'd clear the decks.
What do you think, huh?
I remember that night...
When you took over the benefit.
You were quite the showman.
Thank you.
Always nice to be appreciated.
And you're just going to kill me here?
That's kind of disappointing.
What do you mean?
After all the buildup...
You coming back to life,
turning off the lights in Gotham...
Killing me here just
doesn't show a lot of...
Flair? Hmm? Style?
Panache? Hmm?
Go on, boy. Spit it out.
- I can take it.
- I'm Bruce Wayne.
- I'm aware.
- I am the ruling elite.
My company is the machine
that keeps the cogs
- of Gotham running.
- Wow.
Killing me should mean something!
And you're telling me no
one's going to see it?
You're saying I need an audience?
Oh. Look,
I know you're just trying to buy time
so you can escape.
But your point is still valid.
Saddle up, boys!
We're taking this show on the road!
And I know just the spot.
Come on. Uh-uh-uh.
Not you, old chap.
The prince of Gotham deserves
a public death. His butler,
not so much. Kill him.
- No!
- Bruce!
This is what you've been training for.
You're gonna be all right on your own.
I will see you again.
You carry on, son. You carry on.
Strangely intimate.
Come on.
Try not to get any blood
on the couch. I might
come back for that.
Help!
Somebody help me! Help!
- Help!
- Hello?
Over here!
Oh, oh, thank God.
There's not much time.
Cut me loose! Hurry!
What's that car doing in here?
It doesn't matter. Cut me loose.
You-you look familiar.
Yes. I'm... I happen to
be the mayor of Gotham.
So free me,
and I promise there will
be a handsome reward.
Oh, it-it really is you,
the mayor of Gotham in the flesh.
Yes! Now stop standing there
and get me out of here.
I don't... I don't
know. What did you do?
What? Ah. I'm gonna die here
listening to this moron.
- Just cut the ropes!
- Okay, okay! Okay.
Oh, God.
Hurry!
Fine! Come on then. What
are you waiting for?
- You in a rush to die, old man?
- Who's gonna kill him?
- Who's gonna do it?
- I want to do it.
- I'll do it.
- What?
What, you three?
You three left here to take out
the rubbish, were you?
You, Mr. Machine Gun, by the suit
of armor, what, you're gonna
shoot me in the grill, are you?
What about you with the
crowbar, by the sofa?
Gonna cave in my skull?!
And how 'bout you, Mr. Machete?
Come on in, sunshine. Don't be shy.
Your mother wasn't. Chop-chop.
Who are you talking to, old man?
Me!
Where's Bruce?
That lunatic Jerome took him.
No, please. No.
Dance!
Get him! Squash her!
Get the old lady. No, the fat guy.
Put your back into it.
Oh...
Well, we're off to a good start.
What do you say, Bruce?
Want to have some fun
before the main event?
Bullock's pulling messages
from the tip line.
You said Bruce was able to convince Jerome
to kill him in front of an audience?
Yeah, he was trying to buy
himself some more time.
And I'd be proud if I
wasn't so bloody terrified.
I see it's given way to bedlam again.
Jerome's acolytes
have occupied places all over town.
So finding an audience
won't be the issue.
Question is where.
We got 'em.
They're in Anders Park,
the cathedral, the zoo.
They've taken over the Hillside
Conservatory, the courthouse,
and the Boardwalk Circus.
Jerome was raised in a circus.
Have a strike force and all
available units meet us there.
I'll put out the call
on the way. Let's roll.
Got to be honest, Bruce,
you don't make the
world's funniest clown.
- But...
- Ooh.
We can fix that.
Aw, shut up, you big baby.
Let's turn that frown...
upside-down.
Gabe! We have to find
Ed Nygma and kill him!
Gabe, where...
Your monkey's cleared out.
And what's that you
were saying about Nygma?
Looks like we're not the only
ones trying to kill that guy.
Now, where is he?
I'm sorry, what?
Speak up.
What are you doing in my house?
Whatever we want.
You're finished, Oswald.
Now, where's Nygma?
I don't know.
Think.
What?
I said think.
Oh, I heard you. I'm just
surprised you knew the word.
Speaking of words, any last ones?
Babs said not to kill
him until we have Nygma.
I don't work for Barbara Kean.
Stop pretending that you
are anything but muscle!
Yes, you used to be someone in Gotham,
but those days are past!
Remember when I put a knife
in your mom's back?
That was awful, wasn't it?
Her crying, bleeding out.
You just holding her as she died.
You never did anything about it.
Yet.
Nah.
You had your chance to kill me.
Stop turning us against each other.
We're taking him with us.
Oh, if you think I am
going anywhere with you...
You realize you have to carry him now.
Son of a bitch.
Oh, I missed.
Is there a plan for all of this madness?
These people don't want a
plan... They want an excuse.
The mother who dreams
of strangling her child.
The husband who wants to stab his wife.
All they want is someone to tell them...
"Do it.
Kill them. It doesn't matter."
It doesn't.
Ooh, I love this game!
- One, please.
- You, sir.
No, no, no, no.
Please, no, no.
You won't get away with it.
I already did. Now shush.
I need to concentrate.
A few dozen brainwashed maniacs
can't keep the city hostage forever.
Well, duh.
So what's the point?
The point
is that all these people
out here, looting, robbing,
killing,
they're the people who wash your car,
who pour your coffee,
who take out your trash.
And what happened the
moment the lights went out?
They showed their true faces.
They showed how quickly
they want to open up
your rich boy veins and
bathe in your blue blood.
That...
is the point.
That's not true.
There are good people in Gotham.
Like who?
The sheep who lock their doors
and crawl under their beds?
Face it, kid,
Gotham has no heroes.
- No, no, no.
- Hey.
Foul!
He pushed me. Did you see that?
You want to kill someone,
let's get on with it. Come on!
You're so boring, Bruce.
No!
Huh. Sorry.
Yo.
Ah.
Did that hurt?
Not much.
You try.
Stop.
All right.
Enough dilly-dally.
To the main event.
Where the hell is our backup?
Still two minutes out.
Most were waylaid by another
riot on the west side.
Yeah, but we can't wait, mate.
All right, so... we go in,
find Bruce, get him to safety,
then we go after Jerome.
- Ready?
- Not really.
Yeah, we all know why we're here!
Here comes Jerome, everybody!
Hear ye, hear ye, gather round.
The show is about to... begin!
Let me hear.
Come on, now.
Shut up!
That's better.
Well, I think we can all agree
tonight was a rousing success.
We brought this miserable
city to its knees.
So, how to thank the best
darn cult of fanatics
a messiah like myself
could ever hope for?
I give you...
Cue!
Oh. Yeah. Yes, yes sir.
I give you the climax
of our festivities.
The billionaire prince of Gotham...
Bruuuuce...
Wayne!
Well, so what do you say, Bruce?
Shall we end the night with a bang?
Or better yet... a boom?
Boom, boom, boom, boom, boom...
All right.
What's next?
Death by a thousand cuts, very poetic.
I like that.
Slice!
Nailed it.
All right, folks.
This is very important.
Whatever you do,
please, definitely try this at home.
Preferably on a family member.
Giddyup. Whoo, doggie!
Yee-haw!
You ready, partner?
Oh, good Lord.
Strike force just arrived.
They're coming in.
Detective Gordon, you're just
in time for the big finish.
Nobody move!
Find him.
I'll find Jerome.
So...
here we are.
I suppose I underestimated you, Barbara.
It's the curse of great beauty.
How did it go?
You put together what
happened to Ed's librarian,
turned him against me.
Honestly, wasn't too hard.
And then, together, you hatched a plan
to destroy everything
I made and kill me?
Pretty much.
And brother,
did you ever take the bait.
Well, I hope you're happy
at the head of the table.
You know, the table is
more or less littered
with dead old dudes,
but, hey, it's a place to grow.
And now you got what you want,
you don't need Ed anymore.
Uh-uh.
My, my, it didn't take you
long to turn on each other.
You know, I think of it
as a limited partnership
that needs dissolving.
So... I help you find Ed...
Hmm. Things go better for me?
I don't... you kill me?
That about it?
Yeah.
Oh, Bruce?
Where are you, boy?
Come on out, boy.
I won't hurt ya.
Bruce, darling.
Oh, Brucie...
You ruined my show, Bruce.
Hiding is just gonna make things worse.
I didn't come here to hide.
I wanted you to follow me.
You're going to pay
for what you've done.
You're going to call Ed,
tell him you're alive,
tell him... Oh, I don't care.
But find out where he is.
- Why don't you call him?
- Because he's not stupid.
He knows that now you're no longer
the head of the underworld
or anything else,
we don't need him anymore.
It is our time to rule.
You understand if I feel
compelled to refuse?
Give me five minutes.
- He won't refuse.
- I'd do it in three.
Why you got to do that? What?
- Cut me down like that in front of people.
- I'm just saying...
Will the two of you shut up?!
Give up Nygma, save your own ass.
Live to love another day. Hey?
Wow.
What's going on?
You have a weird look on your face.
Like, weirder than normal.
You're right.
I should want him dead.
"Should"?
Oswald...
you loved him, and he betrayed you.
Actually, I don't know that I did.
Love him.
- Not really.
- What?
Ed was right.
I thought I loved him...
because he saw me as no
one had since my mother.
But I killed Isabelle...
I'm pretty sure her name is Isabella,
but go on.
Because I wouldn't share him.
Ed said love is sacrifice.
I should have been able to
sacrifice my happiness for his.
I couldn't.
But I'm ready now.
I won't... call... Ed.
I won't let you hurt him!
So you'd rather die than give up
the man who tried to kill you?
I would!
Isn't that crazy?
Yes.
It is.
Guess you're not as smart
as you thought you were.
He didn't give you up after all.
You're in this together.
- But why?
- Because
I didn't want to just take what
you had.
I wanted to take what you believed.
I wanted you
to die...
knowing that you were incapable
of loving another person.
But I can.
I just proved that, right?
Now does that mean I passed?
- Ed?
- I...
don't know what it means.
I have to tell you...
this is way more fun
than I was expecting.
We make a good team, you and me.
You killed Alfred.
Is that what this is about?
Yeesh.
Are all rich kids this close
with their butlers?
Oh!
This is about doing what's right.
You want to be a hero!
Tell you what, buddy...
I'll give you a fighting chance.
Let's do this mano y mano,
my little conquistador.
Come on.
What kind of hero tackles
someone from behind?
Let it out!
That's it.
Let it out.
Do it.
Aah!
Alfred!
Bruce!
I thought you were dead.
Can't get rid of me that
easily, can you, mate?
Oh, come here.
Behind you!
Ow.
Word of Jerome's arrest
is spreading quick.
Streets are already quieter.
Soon as the docs reattach his face,
he's off to Arkham.
You wish I would've shot him?
Eh, he'd probably just
- come back from the dead again.
- Probably.
At least you get to say you
punched a man's face off.
That's something, right?
Jim?
Sorry, what?
Come on.
Let me buy you breakfast.
Well, got to say...
the clown makeup was way more terrifying
than the damage
underneath, Master Bruce.
Did I ever tell you that
I don't like clowns?
Well...
in a couple of days,
you'll be back to your old self.
I guarantee it.
You ready to tell me what happened?
When Jerome took me away...
I thought they were going to kill you.
Shall I tell you what I thought?
I thought how proud I was of you.
Of the man that you've become.
I almost killed him, Alfred.
Ah, but you didn't, now, did you?
You controlled your anger.
It wasn't just anger.
After everything Jerome had done,
after all the pain
he caused,
the idea of killing him felt...
It felt right.
Yes.
It felt like justice.
There's a very fine line, Master Bruce,
between justice...
and vengeance.
I know.
But that doesn't mean there isn't one.
No, it doesn't.
I knew where the line
was tonight, Alfred.
I didn't cross it.
Well, that's the first rule.
What do you mean?
Well, I started training you
so you could defend yourself.
Well, we're well past that, aren't we?
But what's all this training for?
What are you gonna do with it?
I don't know.
Nor do I.
But if you keep going,
you're gonna need rules.
Rules that you cannot
and you will not break,
never mind what the reason,
never mind what the circumstance.
I will not kill.
Say it again.
Then let's get to work.
Tonight was close.
We could have lost Gotham for good.
Soon, we will act,
and you will be called upon.
They've done a wonderful
job erasing the scars.
Are you prepared?
Yes. But I still don't understand
how I can help save Gotham.
Never fear.
You are only part of the plan.
Are you sure about this?
You know what must happen
if he refuses.
I know.
No one refuses the Court.
- Uncle Frank?
- Hello, Jim.
It's been a long time.
Ed... I love you.
I know you believe that now.
So you need to listen
to me when I tell you
by doing this... it will change you.
I've killed before, Oswald.
Not like this.
This won't be a crime of passion
or self-preservation.
This will be the cold-blooded murder
of someone you love.
I don't love you.
You need me, Edward Nygma.
Just as I need you.
You cannot have one without the other.
You killed Isabella.
The point is...
That is the point!
You can't talk your way
out of this, Oswald.
I have wanted you to suffer
as I've suffered.
You killed her,
so you die.
When I met you
you were a nervous,
jittery loser.
You were nothing.
I created Edward Nygma.
And I am the only one in the world
who truly sees you as you are.
Who you can still become.
You can't do this.
Ed, are you listening to me?
I'm listening.
Say something.
I loved her, Oswald.
And you killed her.
www.tvsubtitles.net